<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Sam&#39;s Engineering Stuff</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Sam&#39;s Engineering Stuff</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 16:32:27 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Point Bw Points</title>
      <link>/post/2023/03/28/point-bw-points/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 16:32:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2023/03/28/point-bw-points/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s another short post on a problem I solved today. Suppose you have a point and want to see if it&amp;rsquo;s between two other points. If you&amp;rsquo;re working in a 2D space, you can use a solution along the lines of this one from Bryce Boe, but it&amp;rsquo;s not obvious how it would generalize to higher dimensions.
So I thought I&amp;rsquo;d take a different approach: what do we mean when we say a point is &amp;ldquo;between two points?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jacobian Trajectory Generation</title>
      <link>/post/2023/03/23/jacobian-trajectory-generation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Mar 2023 14:08:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2023/03/23/jacobian-trajectory-generation/</guid>
      <description>I wanted to make a mini-post with a sort of cute problem I solved today: let&amp;rsquo;s say you want your robotic arm to travel from one joint-space position to another, but along the way you want it to follow a Cartesian end-effector trajectory. This actually isn&amp;rsquo;t such an unrealistic scenario! You&amp;rsquo;re basically constraining the start and end to be &amp;ldquo;sort of reasonable&amp;rdquo; (something you might want to do, given that 7+dof arms can have weird/slow ik), but you only care about the end effector path in between them, not the whole joint trajectory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Problem 14 Part 1</title>
      <link>/post/2023/03/19/problem-14-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 16:49:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2023/03/19/problem-14-part-1/</guid>
      <description>I recently saw a post on Gwern&amp;rsquo;s blog on an interesting problem in probability and expected value:
A shuffled deck of cards has an equal number of red and black cards. When you draw a red card from the deck, you get $1, and when you draw a black card you lose $1. You can stop whenever you want. If the deck has $N$ cards, what is the expected value of playing this game?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 22:24:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Who are you? My name is Sam Scheele! I&amp;rsquo;m a master&amp;rsquo;s student in computer science, specializing in robotics and computational perception.
What is this place? This is a place for me to write about technical stuff. My current plan is for said stuff to be pretty much entirely math, computer science, and engineering concepts, but I also like to get my hands dirty doing woodworking and electronics projects. Depending on my motivation to write those up and how well I think they&amp;rsquo;ll translate to a blog format (currently, it seems to me that videos are better for physical things), the blog might end up evolving to cover projects of all sorts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Latex Packages</title>
      <link>/post/2023/03/14/latex-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 22:03:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2023/03/14/latex-packages/</guid>
      <description>I like to have the ability to run things locally on my computer, but getting LaTeX to work has always been a pain because of the package system. It tells me that I&amp;rsquo;m missing packages, but they aren&amp;rsquo;t on the AUR and I&amp;rsquo;ve never been willing to invest the time to figure out how to install them. But now that I&amp;rsquo;m working on my thesis I devoted the time to figure it out and I&amp;rsquo;m posting it here so I don&amp;rsquo;t forget.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kalman Filtering 1: Motivation and LUMVE</title>
      <link>/post/2023/03/12/kalman-filtering-1-motivation-and-lumve/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 13:44:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2023/03/12/kalman-filtering-1-motivation-and-lumve/</guid>
      <description>Welcome back to my Kalman filtering notes! In this post we&amp;rsquo;ll first back up and talk about when and why we would want to use a Kalman filter, and we&amp;rsquo;ll go all the way to deriving a filter with the same properties as KF.
Kalman Filter Setup and Motivation Suppose you&amp;rsquo;re designing a satellite that needs to estimate its location in space very precisely. The two most obvious ways to do this are to use GPS and to infer your location by measuring it relative to background stars.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kalman Filtering: Intro</title>
      <link>/post/2023/03/10/kalman-filtering-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 22:38:16 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2023/03/10/kalman-filtering-intro/</guid>
      <description>This is the first in a series of posts on the Kalman Filter! Over the series, we&amp;rsquo;ll first derive a filter with the same properties as the KF, then the KF itself, and finally more advanced variants such as EKF and UKF.
I&amp;rsquo;ll assume for this series that you have some knowledge of linear algebra and probability theory. However, a quick refresher never hurt anyone, so the remainder of this post will cover that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Puzzle: Counting to 100</title>
      <link>/post/2023/03/07/puzzle-counting-to-100/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 13:18:41 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2023/03/07/puzzle-counting-to-100/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s a puzzle I found in &amp;ldquo;The Moscow Puzzles&amp;rdquo;, by Boris Kordemsky and Martin Gardner:
Person 1 can call any number from 1 to 10. Person 2 can then increment the last called number by any whole number from 1 to 10, then it&amp;rsquo;s Person 1&amp;rsquo;s turn again, and so on. The first person to call 100 wins. Give a strategy that allows Person 1 to win this game every time</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, world!</title>
      <link>/post/2023/03/07/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 12:30:35 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2023/03/07/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>Hello, world!
I made this site based on a very minimal hugo theme. Despite the fact that this theme is only 150 lines of code, I still don&amp;rsquo;t understand it! There are two reasons for this:
I&amp;rsquo;m not familiar with Hugo (the static site generator I&amp;rsquo;m using) or really web development There seem to be a lot of magic constants in hugo that I don&amp;rsquo;t like. I think this was part of an effort to make Hugo &amp;ldquo;creator-friendly&amp;rdquo; by hiding complexity from users of the tool.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
